welcome to cultivating wisdom with john
riverkids it's a pleasure to be here
again with all of you
uh we do this uh we live stream this
every saturday morning
at 10 a.m uh eastern time
uh we're coming to the end we're coming
to the end of our journey
we've had a long journey um through the
eastern traditions of buddhism and
taoism
and then we have picked up the journey
through the western traditions we've
gone through epicureanism and stoicism
and now we're into the final stretch
when we look at cultivating wisdom
within the culminating
tradition of neoplatonism and so i'm
excited to see
how this comes together
so if you're joining us for the first
time please
check for this uh in the description for
this video and you'll find links
uh to all of what i've just described uh
available to you
i recommend going back to if you're just
joining us go back to lesson one
from meditating with john viveki work
your way through the lessons and then
come into
uh cultivating wisdom with john vicki
work your way through the lessons
and hopefully you'll be able to join uh
into the
into the community and you'll be able to
keep meeting with us
in the course all right so for today
we are going to do the usual practice
we're going to sit first
and then i will move to the whiteboard
with the help
of my my son and uh amar
and we'll do the dharma talk or maybe we
now that we're in the western tradition
we should call it the logos talk
um and then we'll take any hopefully
this will be some time
for some questions all right so get
yourself in position
uh set your phones on do not disturb
we'll begin as i said with chanting and
we'll begin
together when i say the word begin
begin
one
begin your silence set
slowly come out of your practice trying
his best to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
all right we'll move over to the
whiteboard
okay so want to talk to you about
neoplatonism
and it is
it's exciting to be here uh because i
agree with the work of arthur bush lewis
um that neoplatonism is the cognitive
cultural grammar of the spirituality of
the west
the west very broadly considered
i'm including islam within that the sufi
tradition
is definitely deeply informed and
empowered
by the neoplatonic tradition
christianity
especially the mystical uh trans within
christianity especially
eastern orthodox christianity deeply
again
informed transformed and powered by
neoplatonism
the mystical traditions within judaism
um
kabbalah being one example also deeply
deeply informed
uh by neoplatonism i'm gonna just get a
couple of books i'm off camera for a sec
so just a reminder of some of the
texts we can we're using of course the
primary one
we're going through absolutely mandatory
is mcclellan's
the wisdom of hypatia we're now moving
into
what he calls the the grove what i'm
calling university we've done primary
school with epicureanism
high school with stoicism and now we're
into the university
i mentioned arthur versus lewis i highly
recommend this little gem of a book
perennial philosophy
in which he makes the argument that i've
just made to you
amongst many other books you can he's
very prolific and very scholastic
um i recommend this book um
for you know a very good very good
introduction to neoplatonism
within the context of the argument on
how it is the cultural cognitive grammar
of the spirituality of the west
another a couple of really good academic
books
this won't mean much to you now uh but
this is probably
the one of the most important books it's
called theorgia and the soul by gregory
shaw this is an academic book
so it's it's it's not a practical book
but it helps to explain theorgia or
what's called theorgy
and that needs a lot of explanation i
would complement that book
obviously mcclellan has practices around
their ja
kupperman's book i don't agree with any
everything in
both uh mcclellan and kepperman but
nevertheless
these are two great books um on
the neoplatonic practice of theater
one more academic book i would recommend
don't be put off by the title it's a
very good academic book
divination and human nature a cognitive
history of intuition
and classical antiquity so a lot of
practices that within our time have
degenerated into psychic
and magical practices they weren't
really understood
uh it's not proper to understand them
the way we understand them now
as for example strzok argues um
and other people have argued we should
look at a lot of these theorgic
practices
instead of ways of cultivating a
profound insight
or profound intuition implicit learning
and aspiration and so i'll talk about
all of those things from a cognitive
scientific perspective
rather than any kind of
supernaturalistic perspective which is
exactly what this
this book is about so that of course is
part of the challenge we're facing
um i love neoplatonism i i consider
myself a neoplatonist
more than any other label that you might
apply to me including buddhist or taoist
and what i want to say about that
is because i love it so deeply
and respect it so profoundly i'm also
aware
i think perhaps
i'm also aware because not perhaps i'm
aware because
of that of its dangers and its defects
and i'm not recommending that we should
go back
to uh ancient forms of neoplatonism
i do think we should take a look at uh
their surviving living traditions of
neoplatonism
uh with especially within eastern
orthodox christianity that's the one
that's often closest to us
but those of you who are from a muslim
background sufism
etc and so
what i'm proposing instead is what we've
done before which is
can we exact from ancient neoplatonism
a set of practices that we can weave
into uh
the practices the ecology of practices
that have emerged out of our studies
together
of epicureanism and stoicism such that
we get something viable and vital for us
today
all right so today what i want to do is
i want to give you a bit of a background
this will complement the background of
mclennan about what neoplatonism is
nobody in the ancient world called
themselves a neoplatonous this is a
this is a modern scholastic term
everybody in this tradition considered
themselves
a follower of plato we call it
neoplatonism because
the neoplatonists while they saw
themselves as continuous with plato
actually were tremendously innovative
and i would say in a very
uh beneficial way um so what i want to
do is show you
how they're kind of like the grand
unified field theory
of western spirituality and wisdom
cultivation they basically are the
summative
integrative theory and ecology of
practices
for western spirituality so what i want
to do is show you
how they drew from some though some of
the most important sources
uh obviously from plato that's going to
be a primary source
but from aristotle and uh from the
stoics as well
if i had a little bit more time i talked
about some of the influence of the
skeptics but i don't
that will come out when i do the series
after socrates so what did they get
from plato okay well obviously plato
is where we get the um
more than just the portrayal we get the
exemplification of socrates in the
platonic dialogues we get to see
socrates
practicing dialectic engendering
dialogues
trying to afford radical transformation
and we've
we've seen how all of these traditions
as we've said
socrates is to the western traditions
what sidhartha is to buddhism
right that the epicureans the stoics
even more so the stoics were
internalizing socrates and plato it's
taken
up now the interesting thing about the
neoplatonus is unlike the stoics who
tend to emphasize socrates more
the neoplatonus as their name declares
uh we're
are much more focused on plato so what
what are some of the
ideas they got from plato
well one of the most important and we're
already using it to some degree
in uh the practice we did last week of
invoking the logos
plato gate created the first um psyche
logos tsuke logos
the first psy psychological theory right
tsuki logos
the first right logos of the suitcase
psychology uh right psychological theory
in history and he used it in order to
try and explain
he was trying to figure out why people
fell into self-deceptive
self-destructive behavior
now the reason why i'm invoking this is
that this insight of plato has proved to
be
such a profound insight we keep
rediscovering it
in the west within within western
psychology i'll give you a couple of
answers when i
sorry examples once i explain it to you
so what plato was interested in is well
why do we fall into self-deception
so what's the basic idea that he got
from socrates we fall into
self-deception
when the salience and the intensity of
something and we've seen this all the
way through this tradition
when the salience and the intensity of
something is uncoupled from
the truth and our understanding of it
now when it's uncoupled and we're in a
state of wonder
and the salience of the intensity is
beyond our current understanding but
that
motivates us to question and to wonder
well that's right to to seek more
understanding and that's socrates
because wisdom begins in such wonder but
the opposite of that
is something like what harry frankford
calls the phenomena
where the salience and the intensity is
uncoupled from
our concern for truth and understanding
such that we
don't question we don't want we don't
wonder
we have a pretentious certainty and we
run headlong
into and we jump to conclusions and that
is
the primary way in which we fall into
self-deception now plato took that idea
but he wanted to understand
well how do how does how does the
salience and the understanding
becomes so unglued and he looked at
something
it's a very powerful experience for all
of us and one we encounter in a
spiritual pathway
he looked at inner conflict
and there's a lot of current cognitive
science that backs up the model i'm now
going to talk to you about
he noticed that let's say um you i want
to lose weight
right so i want to lose weight and then
there's a part of me
that knows right and he called this his
reason he sort of put it and he plato
was uh for his time one of the least
sexist thinkers he recommended that
women could also rule also be in the
army
but right he's still in the ancient
world athens is a horrible place for
women
in athens but he represented this with a
man in
in your head and what what this this is
a
part of you that can grasp
long-term goals
it can right it's capable of abstract
thought in that sense that's things that
are currently present
it allows you to grab abstract goals it
allows you to see the abstract or
invisible properties of things
so i'm right i i i want to
improve my health that's a very abstract
phenomenon it's long-term
and i'm motivated by you know
the truth of things that seems to what
happens is i come home and there's the
chocolate cake on the counter and
ah i want the chocolate cake it's super
super salient and he said this is like a
monster on us
and sorry um yeah i want to keep it
parallel
structure for you guys uh there's the
monster
and then he called this part you the
part of you that's your appetites
and that means sexual food everything
and he put this sort of in your stomach
and your genitalia
all right so this doesn't grasp
long-term goals
it's about what's happening right here
right now
it's urgent it's superficial it's super
salient
it's intense and it works in terms of
pleasure and pain
okay so in contrast short term
superficial works in terms of pleasure
and then in between right there is
i'm going to erase this now although
i'll keep doing this parallel structure
just in between was
the fact that we're social cultural
beings
i'm going to use the greek word here
because we don't have
a good english word for this
we do not have a good english word for
this so
the greek word is thymos it's in your
chest
so think of where you feel all the
social emotions
where you feel pride and honor and
notice what my hands are doing expansion
or guilt
and shame the contraction right so it's
that movement that's the thymus and he
said this is like a lion
and as you may have expected it's in
your chest
so this doesn't work in terms of
pleasure and pain or truth and falsity
works in terms of honor and shame pride
and guilt
this is the socio-cultural aspect of you
and so this is the part of you
that it doesn't work in terms of ab
completely abstract
uh long-term goals but it's not just at
right the the urgent bidding of
the current stimulus instead it has to
do
with your connectedness to other people
and your connectedness to other people
now i put it this way you could put this
on top uh because
maybe it has to do with morality
the ordering is just to so it lines up
like with
with you as an enacted symbol of this
and here's the idea right
the man can actually learn
it's capable of forming theories and
explanations
the lion isn't really capable of
learning but the lion can be trained
so the man can learn the theory
sorry for the sexist language and that
theory
can be learned to use to train the lion
that's what we're doing by the way and
notice
that this ultimately requires
sociocultural interaction
it requires that we do things with
others because that's how that's the
that's
the he chose the lion because the lions
are social cats right
they form prides and notice the
association to pride
by the way okay so you learn the theory
and then you can train the lion and then
you can tame the monster you don't want
to kill
anything because we need all of these
sometimes you need your monster
you need to eat you need to run away
from the threat
sometimes of course the lion should be
predominant because it's a social
situation
and you should be picking up on other
people appropriately treating them
as persons within a community of persons
of people
and then of course there's times we're
doing it more here we emphasize the man
and we're trying to learn
when we get this properly
organized we can deal with the fact that
the man
on his own is largely impotent
when i come in and i see the chocolate
cake my knowing
having the beliefs that i shouldn't eat
it and this this is supported by a lot
of evidence by the way is
largely insufficient
even almost impotent at stopping me from
eating the cake but if i
learn about how to improve my health and
join weight watchers
or maybe join a sangha and learn
meditation
right then i can use the social power
of the lion to implement the theory
and tame the monster
so when we do and we know all about this
this is anorexia this is and we've been
talking about this all through
epicureanism
and stoicism this is inner peace now
plato has a brilliant idea about this
he has the what we're trying to do he
says this is something like an
inner form of justice we're trying to
get everything
in the right relationship so that each
can get the most
life it can without
right diminishing the lives of the two
others
so if the lion is too much it will right
it could kill the monster you can think
of people
who are super ascetic and destroy uh
their bodies
and are are irrational right
the man of course can fall into all
kinds of rumination
and anxiety and and screw this all up
and of course the monster can overwhelm
what you want is you want something like
a just
society within and when that happens
you get the the the the full the fullest
possible being you can have each one
lives the most it can
without trespassing or at the expense of
the others
so they have the although individually
each one could be
greater there is an optimal relationship
between
the the inner society and you have a
fullness of being
and one of plato's great understandings
one of his great insights is one of the
things that drives our spiritual
pursuits
is we want this inner peace this
fullness of being
this is a a meta meta drive in addition
to all of
our how we try to satisfy our individual
drives or desires
we want the satisfaction of our desires
to
be something that affords and empowers
anorexia this inner peace this fullness
of being so inner peace isn't
just a lack of conflict it's a fullness
of being
it is to realize yourself in a profound
way
okay
so the neoplatons have a very
sophisticated
they have a very sophisticated way of
making use of this psychological theory
now that theory it just keeps coming
back some of you will recognize freud in
it
some of you will recognize uh the dual
or what's now called triple processing
models that are all the rage within
cognitive science and cognitive
psychology so we keep coming back to
this
because so much evidence keeps
converging on this
but here's the idea that plato that
really thought
so when i don't have inner justice
a virtue he called sophoson when i don't
have that inner justice
what's going to happen is i'm not going
to have my salience and my understanding
properly and my actions
properly coordinated so if i'm
if i haven't cultivated that inner
justice which is one important
poll or aspect of wisdom then when i
come into a situation let's for example
the chocolate cake the salience of the
cake overwhelms
my understanding and my grasp of the
truth and that is exactly why i fall
into this self-destructive bit i deceive
myself oh it's okay to eat the cake
right now
and then that's self-destructive
behavior so the imbalance
the imbalance causes self-deception
it actually disconnects me from
the world i'm not connected to
the reality of things appropriately this
connects me from
my future self that i'm trying to
cultivate it will ultimately disconnect
me from others
because i will act for example greedily
i will not act properly virtuously
and if you say well i'll act morally
then you're starting to invoke the lion
and you're already starting to move to
right towards the coordination
so let's do the opposite then
let's say i've started to cultivate some
adoraxia
what does that mean well it means i'm
increasing i'm decreasing my
self-deceptive
self-destructive behavior
okay what does that mean
well that means actually because of that
i start to
see into in sight i start to see into
the real patterns of the
world and we'll come back to what plato
means by these real patterns
and i see not just in the sense of
getting an idea
i am fitted i'm more appropriately
fitted so you can even put
realize right the real patterns of the
world
now as i start to pick up on the real
patterns of the world
i actually gain some real knowledge i
start to understand
how particular patterns operate
i can then internalize that i can use
that understanding
of real patterns to see
into the real patterns of my own psyche
i look into the patterns of my own
psyche
which means i get a better oh wait
that's a better way in which
the psyche should be coordinated and
organized
and you see what starts happening now i
get more anoraxia
i reduce my self-deceptive
self-destructive behavior
i start to fit more into the real
patterns
the real patterns can be an internal
life and you know what this is
you've seen it before this is reciprocal
opening
it's no coincidence that you know mark
lewis
came up with the idea of addiction as
reciprocal narrowing
and then he acknowledged to me that it
has an opposite which is reciprocal
opening it plugs into this deep deep
model of plato this cycle
is called anagage
now we have a meta drive for inner peace
and then what plato saw is we also have
a meta drive here
in addition to whatever satisfy whatever
satisfies our desires or our wants
we want what satisfies it to be real or
true
i can give you tons of examples i'll
just give you a quick one i do this all
the time in my class
i'll ask my students how many of you are
in a really
satisfying romantic relationship they
put up their hands
okay how many of you would want to know
if your partner was cheating on you
even if that means the complete
destruction of the relationship about 95
of the people keep up their hands
they're willing to sacrifice all of this
pleasure
all of this comfort all of this joy
because it's not
real okay so we
want to be connected so the idea in
platonic spirituality is spirituality is
about
satisfying these two fundamental
metadrives
the drive for inner peace and the drive
to be in contact with what's real and
what plato says is if we do it right
if we cultivate wisdom with the right
ecology and practices
these will be mutually reinforcing in a
positive feedback cycle
and we'll get reciprocal opening and
that's anagarge
that's anagarge so neoplatonism
is basically the philosophy religion
of anagogy
okay so what are these real patterns we
won't get through all of this today
and i still have to tell you next time
we're going to be together
how the neoplatonists draw from
aristotle how they draw from the stoics
and then what the basic form of practice
so the introduction is going to take
today
and next saturday and then we'll get
into the ecology of practices but you
need to understand this background
just like i gave you a background for
epicureanism and i gave you the
background for stoicism
so what are these real patterns that i
mentioned
well we already make a distinction
in science that's helpful to start us we
make a distinction between patterns that
are just correlations
and patterns that are causal
and one of the big things you learn and
it takes a lot of
discipline you have to discipline
yourself with discernment
and open yourself up to the disclosure
of the world that's what a really good
experiment is
in order to make this i'm i
i'm gonna expect a little bit of
frustration i'm tired of people
who like
don't appreciate enough the discipline
right of science science that means
sciencia to know
you have to right
we are so beset by self-deceptive
cognitive biases that we need to do a
lot
of training in order to distinguish
correlations from causation
that's what science is all about and
it's really hard it's really hard
and if you're going to say i reject
science then tell me please
your better method for distinguishing
causation from correlation
because if you don't have one i'm not
going to listen to you
i'm not going to listen to you
so why am i emphasizing that because
there is a tendency for people who are
attracted to neoplatonism
to take an anti-scientific attitude that
is not
hypatia's attitude hypatia was one of
the greatest
scientists of her time and there is a
deep
and long-standing tradition of the
interconnection between science
and neoplatonism uh john spencer's book
right uh the eternal law uh argues for
for
the fact the historical fact that many
of the pivotal figures at the beginning
of the scientific revolution
were deeply uh influenced explicitly
by neoplatonism
all right
so when i was being brought up in a
christian fundamentalist family
right i would hear things like you know
things have gotten so much worse since
we took prayer
out of the schools right by the way
that's not true but let's say it was
now that's a correlation the problem
with correlations yeah two things
are in relation correlation but you
don't know
is a causing b
your intuitions will say that but it can
turn out that it's b that's causing a
or often a and b have no causal relation
they're both being caused by
c and your intuitions
and your untrained observation can't
distinguish these
there's things you have to do so
let's go back to the correlation well we
took prior
prior to the school and crime rates went
up actually it didn't but let's say
that's the case
well i want you to notice something else
here's greenhouse gases
going up across time here's caribbean
piracy
it's been going down across time
do you see what the problem is
greenhouse gases are going up because
we have stopped practicing caribbean
piracy so we need to get on some wooden
ships and sail around the caribbean
and that will that will deal with global
warming now you laugh and it's absurd
but notice that many times things are
absurd because we are confusing
correlation and causation
so the first step
the first step at getting to the real
patterns that plato was on about was a
careful reflection
trying to distinguish initially the
causal patterns
from the correlational patterns
practicing
doing that now he didn't have the
full-blown scientific method
but he saw the necessity of
critical theoretical debate and
discussion in order to try and discern
the difference between correlation
and causation
so using science notice
that we can't as a as an analogy we can
talk about the real patterns we can talk
about
there's patterns of causation like if i
put sugar in water it dissolves
and then those patterns of causation are
actually
maybe i'll do it this way maybe this
makes more sense now the plate the
neoplateness have a
have an upward metaphor but now we have
a more downward metaphor
so here's some causal patterns in the
world
and what scientists do right is they try
to find
deeper structural patterns
right they try to find systems of
patterns
and then they ultimately try to find the
principles
or using a legal term the laws
that regulate those patterns
and this is this is virtually you know
it's a version of what you're trying to
do in
neoplatonism you're trying to realize
first
the patterns that are unfolding in your
environment then
the systems the structures that those
patterns are within
and then ultimately the governing
principles that
ra science is neoplatonic through and
through that ultimately
the governing principles of that
so plato had a theory about this
and it's the idea that we're trying to
come up
we're trying to realize what he called
well he called it the idos
and we translate it very it's it's
this is like translating logos with word
the word word
it's it's a legitimate translation but
it's radically insufficient
and so what i want to talk to you about
next time
is i want to talk to you about the how
plato understood this
but before this seems too strange to you
think about how we did this in
when we did invoking the logos right
we were picking up on the
right the fuses the way things are
unfolding
right and then we were picking up on
the intelligibility the the system the
systematic structure
so we sat like a mountain which is we
got into the basic
presencing right the weight of it then
we sat like a poppy and we tried to turn
and orient ourselves towards the sun
we'll see how plato makes use of the
metaphor of the sun we're trying to
orient our
we're trying to orient ourselves to the
real patterns the causal patterns
and then after we sat like a poppy we
sat like an ocean
we tried to pick up on the overarching
structure
right over our flow in and out arising
and passing away
the system and then right we
right we moved into that into the the
musicality the intelligibility of how it
all makes sense
so we'll see how we're moving through
here and then we pointed towards
the source the ultimate principle
we were doing this we were enacting it
we were invoking it as we
were doing the invocation of the logos
we were
already practicing anagage because as we
did it within
we did it without and as we aligned
within the microcosm
we found it we found the alignment
without the macrocosm
and we started to do the anagogic ascent
so i'm going to talk a lot more next
time about
the plato's theory of the forms and
how that gives us an understanding of a
deeper understanding of anagay and
participation
and then we'll be able to move into
aristotle and how his theory of
knowledge by conformity was taken in by
taken into neoplatonism and then we'll
see what neoplatonism draws
from the stoics in terms of again the
logos
internalization self-discipline
the civic virtues that prepare you for
purification and at one minute
and then we'll be ready to talk about
neoplatonism proper
uh what its main ideas are the
innovations it brought in so like i said
we're both
we'll with this might take one or maybe
even two more
uh lectures i guess that's what this is
sorry so we get the background we needed
because again this is this is the
summative
it's simultaneously the grand unified
theory
and the grand unified ecology of
practices of the entire
western wisdom tradition and that's why
we keep perennially this is verse
lewis's point
we parentally keep turning to it again
and again and again
it is the inexhaustible fountain that we
turn to
for the spirituality that puts us
directly and continuously in touch
with the inexhaustible source of the
intelligibility of being itself for us
and this is simultaneously
something abstract any transcendent in
that sense
but also deeply deeply imminent in the
very guts
think about the tripart soul the ver the
tripart psyche if you
prefer that term right the very guts of
your being
okay so i'm now going to go back
to the meditation pillow jason will
switch the camera
and then what we'll do is we'll take a
look at any questions
uh people might have now please please
be patient with me
neoplatonism is con i can't give you the
background like i could with
epicureanism or stoicism well i actually
i i spread that background over a couple
of talks too i need two or three talks
to give you
what you need for understanding um
and then as we're going along you'll see
i've already tried to indicate
more and more how this right affords
impregnates and and empowers
an ecology of practices that we're going
to take a deep look at together
and then that will bring us uh to the
end
of the wisdom of hypatia
are there any questions
oh uh brett uh thank you for doing the
philosophical fellowship
uh demonstration you're welcome brett
i'm uh uh
i was very i want to thank um everybody
uh uh tracy kira uh rob
uh and of course ammar behind the scenes
uh working his magic
uh we will see um how the philosophical
fellowship
is actually um an important bridging
practice as i indicated
uh uh between like epicureanism
um and aspects of stoicism and we'll see
how it
therefore also prepares us for practices
the practice of dialectic
that's one of the core practices
within neoplaton neoplatonism so there's
actually a pedagogical program
that as you move through elementary
school high school
and uh in university and and that
program is really important
if you skip to the end if you jump to
the conclusion
you are falling into foolishness you're
falling into foolishness
um are there any other questions that
anybody else wants to ask about perhaps
today's
talk there's another question coming up
gazelle good to hear from you again is
correla
is correlation patterns necessarily bad
i have a lot of meaningful quinces in my
life so i worry
um that's
um the way i think
i would put that is all remember always
trying to balance discernment
how we can best see through uh
misleading appearances and disclosure
opening us
ourselves up for how the world may
correct what we see
discernment and disclosure discernment
and disclosure always
in coordination so if
you don't confuse correlation with
causation
if you treat it just as correlation and
don't treat it as
if it is causation then of course
there's no mistake because treating a
correlation as a correlation is treating
it as it is
the danger for us
is it's very hard for our brains who are
prediction-hungry machines
to leave correlations just as
correlations
we start to we start to behave
and believe that there are causes now
some of the correlations might be causes
just because something's a correlation
doesn't preclude it from being a cause
all causes are also correlations it's
just that not all correlations many many
many most correlations
aren't causes and so if there's a
correlation
and you're being i think this is the
right word tempted
into believing that it's a causal
pattern then you have to do the hard
work
we have to do the hard work because it
should be done with in concert with
other people
of you know rational reflection
empirical investigation
uh to to determine if there's good
reason
and good evidence for concluding
that the correlational pattern is a
causal pattern and
like the degree to which you can do that
work is the degree to which you can have
confidence
that you are discovering a causal
pattern
rather than a correlational pattern the
degree to which you can't do the work
and
many of us can't because we don't have
opportunity we don't have resources
or also there's there might be ten are
temperamental
uh issues or trauma issues i i i wanna
be sensitive to all of that
but the degree to which we can't do that
is the degree to which
we have to practice the stoicism we have
to practice realizing that if we treat
cause
correlations as causes we're doing the
projective thing
that the stoics warned us against we
have to do epochae
we have to bracket and realize no i
shouldn't treat this as anything more
than a correlation
any other questions that was an
excellent question
well we're pretty much out of time
anyway i want to thank you all
for joining as always i want to thank
my beloved son jason my dear friend and
techno mage ammar
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video
if it's not against your principles
please follow me on twitter
for updates about these streams updates
about
other things that are happening like
talks i'm giving
or talks i'm recommending or there's
just so much happening right now it's
it's really quite
quite exciting and quite wonderful
please
invite others who might benefit from
sharing this series
or also share uh look connect them up
also to the meditation series perhaps
also to the lecture series awakening for
the meeting crisis
or the dialogue series voices with
verveiki
so please remember we are doing this
every saturday morning
at 10 a.m
continuity of practice is more important
than quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of a
vicious
perfectionism but a virtuous friendship
because in the end there is no enemy
worse than your own mind and body
but there is no friend no ally no true
companion on the path
that is better than your own mind and
body be lamps unto yourselves
and to end to each other take good care
everyone
i'll see you next saturday